Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Both of you, please have a seat.
The birds disappear in the snowy winter.
Although it's not as lively as spring,
winter has its own charm.
Indeed.
What do you think, Lady Fuca?
Your Highness invited me to appreciate
winter's beauty, so I am.
That makes me feel that I'm forcing you.
Actually, it's good to see more of each other, and talk.
In this way we'll become closer, and avoid misunderstandings and rifts.
We are brought together by serving HIs Majesty.
How could we have misunderstandings or rifts?
Winter has reminded me of a story.
Your Highness is learned and educated.
I'd like to hear it.
It's the story of "human swine."
I'm neither learned nor educated.
I don't remember the details well.
It happened during the reign of Emperor Gaozu of Han.
Lady Qi gained favor and offended Empress Lü.
After Empress Lü became the Empress Dowager,
she cut off Lady Qi's hands and feet,
gouged her eyes, cut her ears, and used poison to make her mute.
She locked her in the outhouse.
This punishment is called "human swine".
Lady Qi was one of the most beautiful women of her time.
It's so pathetic that she ended up like that.
Empress Lü was unbearably cruel,
but Lady Qi had only herself to blame.
She was deluded by her favor.
Women can hold deep grudges, and Empress Lü was no exception.
Lady Fuca,
am I right?
- Jinxi.
- My Lady!
Help Lady Fuca to her chair.
Yes.
It is only a story.
What's the matter, Fuca?
Perhaps Lady Fuca was troubled by my lack of skill.
I told it so poorly - she could not understand it.
Why did you tell me that story?
Although Consort Nian is arrogant and domineering,
I admire one of her qualities.
She is ruthless when she is determined.
In the past, someone simply made an offensive remark
and was banished to another palace.
If Consort Nian was abused on Long Street,
I wonder how she would take revenge?
If it happened to Consort Nian, given her temperament,
she would administer the human swine punishment,
or another more painful than death.
Yes, if I were more like Consort Nian,
I wouldn't have allowed myself to be
bullied after I entered the harem.
Sourire, you are greatly favored by His Majesty.
You can do anything you like.
I beg Your HIghness's forgiveness.
I admit my fault.
I will not act like that again.
Fuca, you've always acted so sure of yourself.
Where is this guilt coming from?
I was just telling a story.
I was listening to Consort Astuce.
I beg Your Highness's forgiveness.
Were you?
Whatever it is, we can discuss it later.
Although Sima Qian [a historian in Han dynasty]
wrote as if dictated by Heaven,
he didn't really know what a human swine was like.
As far as I know, human swine is not the worst.
In the Tang Dynasty, concubines were made into human swine,
and then soaked in a wine cask.
This punishment was called ...
"drunken bones".
Even though it was cruel,
she should have expected it
since every action has a consequence.
My Lady, what's the matter with you?
My Lady, please wake up.
I thought she had a strong stomach,
but her boldness was hollow.
Jinxi, Lady Fuca is not feeling well. Help her back.
My Lady...
Both of you!
Come here, over here.
- Carry her away.
- Yes.
Madam, do we need to send for the imperial doctors?
Tell a doctor to visit, but don't spend too much time on her.
Yes.
"Kill the chicken to scare the monkey."
The chicken is dead now.
What does Your Highness want to tell me?
It's good to talk with an intelligent woman like you, Lady Cao.
Conversation becomes effortless.
You are not cruel or vindictive.
If Lady Fuca really offended Your Highness,
you could just send her to the Ministry of Penalty.
You didn't need to stage this trouble.
Your Highness did this to instill fear.
If Your HIghness has something to say,
please say it to me directly.
It usually takes "nine turns to reach your heart", Cao.
I am quite surprised
to be invited to be candid.
I had a cold a few days ago,
so I frequently reminded His Majesty to visit you.
I hope you didn't mind.
I appreciated it, Your Highness.
But although His Majesty was with me,
his heart was with Your Highness
as if his soul had no home.
Lady Cao, you are intelligent.
You shouldn't worry where his heart resides.
“Seeing the person makes it harder to feel detached.”
As long as His Majesty visits you now and then,
assuredly you will gain heaven's favor
by using your clever mind.
Consort Nian's loss of favor created a burden
for you, and affected Princess Wenyi.
His Majesty had not visited you for half a year, had he?
I'm not blessed by Heaven.
I don't expect His Majesty's attention.
It isn't a concern to be treated this way,
except for Princess Wenyi's sake.
If she isn't cherished by her father during childhood,
what will her future bring?
I was so shortsighted.
I wasn't "the smart bird that chooses a good tree to perch on".
And now am in a bleak situation.
I don't blame anyone.
You shouldn't waste time on regret.
The Princess's future depends on you fighting for her.
As for the situation in the past,
it was not shortsighted to align yourself with Consort Nian.
And it was not an easy alliance to form.
But you are still seen as closely affiliated with Consort Nian.
That's not good.
In truth, I am greatly concerned for our future.
I hope that Consort Nian's fall from grace
will not reflect on me.
Consort Nian is impetuous and ruthless.
Your days with her must have been difficult.
You knew I was innocent in the cassava starch incident.
You must have known who used Princess Wenyi to gain favor.
Poor Princess Wenyi.
It was such torture for her at that age.
It makes my heart ache.
As a mother,
seeing your own child suffer,
you must have hurt even more.
But without Consort Nian’s favor,
I wouldn't have been able to give birth to the Princess.
It was reasonable to pay her back for her aid.
But what happened afterward...
she used your child to gain favor for herself.
In fact, you are no less clever than Consort Nian.
You followed her in the past to protect yourself.
Consort Nian is domineering, and I could not defy her.
When Noble Lady Chun fell into the water,
I wanted to warn Your Highness
but it was too late to make any difference.
You have a perceptive mind, Lady Cao,
and were quick to see that Consort Nian would be unreliable.
So, you secretly did me a favor,
I am a person who repays my gratitude.
I could only obey all her orders.
I did not have the strength to act against her.
Unfortunately, Noble Lady Chun was not saved.
Now I dare to ask,
how did Noble Lady Chun lose her footing?
If you are fearful, you don't have to tell me.
Consort Nian was jealous that Lady Chun
was favored at such a young age
and was close to Your Highness.
She was eager to cut off Your Highness's wings.
She was that impatient?
She wasn't afraid that His Majesty would investigate?
Consort Nian sees everyone else as beneath her;
killing a concubine meant nothing to her.
Besides, her death left no trace of a suspect.
When Lady Chun looked for her kite, she overheard
a private meeting between Consort Nian
and General Nian’s subordinate.
That's why she was silenced by Consort Nian.
It is reasonable that Consort Nian wanted
to meet General Nian’s subordinate.
Why would they need to meet secretly?
Consort Nian's expenditures are very high
but her money is not unlimited.
To increase her income,
she passed on the names of those who wished to
buy an official position to General Nian.
Zhao Zhiyuan was re-appointed to
another position by bribing Consort Nian.
How dare she collude with Nian Gengyao
to influence the official appointments in court?
And now, these corrupt officials have formed
a faction supporting Nian Genyao.
You had no choice in being my enemy in the past.
it’s understandable.
Giving birth to Princess Wenyi is a great
contribution to the imperial family.
But after years of supporting Consort Nian,
you were not even on par with
Concubine Beauté who was childless.
It's pitiful.
A mother’s status impacts her child’s future.
Perhaps you do not know.
His Majesty told me only yesterday.
Yingge Khagan was violently murdered less than half a
month after Princess Zhaogui was married to him.
Now that the Princess is widowed, will she return soon?
It would be her blessing to return.
The Princess has to follow the
local custom and marry the new khagan.
How could this humiliation happen to the Princess?
A woman's sole duty is to continue the family lineage.
Even though unwilling, she has to follow their custom.
Falling from a primary wife to a concubine.
I will render my humble service to Your Highness!
I beg Your Highness to protect Princess Wenyi and myself.
I will be infinitely grateful.
I have long admired you, Lady Cao.
Today, we have become close.
It is more than I wished for.
If you feel cold, My Lady,
you can lie down in bed.
I will fill a hot water bottle for you.
Coua,
do you think that others are laughing at me now?
My Lady, you are overthinking.
When I was in high favor,
people were grinding their teeth with resentment.
But now, Concubine Sourire has silently stolen my favor
and never treats me the same way as before.
How could people not laugh at me?
His Majesty has only summoned her a few more times.
His Majesty has not forgotten you, My Lady.
Really?
His Majesty always said that my voice is soft and delicate.
But now that His Majesty is with Concubine Sourire,
he has forgotten everything else.
Without nose, without ears.
Without hands, without feet.
What’s going on, Fuca?
I don't want to be a human swine.
- Human swine?
- I don't want to be a human swine.
Who would do that?
She wants to make me into a human swine!
- It’s impossible.
- Your Highness, help!
- No one would dare!
- I don't want to be a human swine!
No one would!
You!
What has happened to Lady Fuca?
I'm not sure, Your Highness.
A few days ago, My Lady had a talk with
Concubine Sourire and Lady Cao.
She fainted in the pavilion and has been
like this ever since she was revived.
Concubine Sourire ...
Concubine Sourire threatened her?
It makes no sense ...
Lady Cao was there as well.
But she didn’t have such a shock.
I don't want to become a human swine!
My Lady, Lady Fuca has lost her mind.
I heard Lady Fuca became insane and started to
talk incoherently after recovering.
She is afraid to go out and has been hiding in bed.
- Does His Majesty know of this?
- Yes.
Lady Fuca has disrupted the peace of the palace.
His Majesty has placed an order
confining Lady Fuca to her palace
and has only sent a few imperial doctors to treat her.
I thought she was strong.
But just a few words scared away her sanity?
She has a guilty conscience,
and her own fear has driven her insane.
Since His Majesty has sent doctors, they will treat her.
- Go knock on the door.
- Yes.
My Lady, Consort Astuce is here
and needs to see you urgently.
It's rather strange since Consort Astuce never visits us.
Why would she come today?
I don't have time to see her.
Go tell her she will not be involved
in what happened to Lady Fuca.
And I will no longer pursue the oleander incident.
Tell her to do whatever she wants.
Yes
My Lady, the way you deal with people
seems different from before.
I was much too mild-natured in the past.
I tolerated their actions.
It allowed them to walk all over me when my fortune declined.
Lady Fuca's insanity will act as a warning to them.
I'm no longer easy prey.
But you still choose to forgive Consort Astuce this time?
Although she was cruel,
she simply wanted to protect her son.
Lady Fuca has already gone mad.
There is no need for me to pursue her further.
This is enough of a warning for her.
Everyone says that Consort Nian is aggressive and ruthless.
They give way before her iron fist.
Her tactics are effective when dealing with anyone who defies her.
Consort Nian's exclusive favor all these years
has not been without reason.
I should learn the essence of her methods and use it for myself.
I have been "the fish meat between
the knife and chopping board".
Now it's time for a change.
These lucky bags are small and delicate.
You will be able to grab a handful of these on New Year's Eve and have the greatest fortune for next year.
Are you praising my lucky bags,
or teasing me for having large hands?
You are not even appreciative when you're complimented.
Now I don't want to say any more compliments.
Your Highness, here is the yarn you asked for.
Madam Cui.
Censor Zhang Lin got beaten up by State Prince Dun.
- What?
- What are you talking about?
Your Highness, something happened in the imperial court.
What happened?
State Prince Dun came back to Beijing three days ago.
But he was late to court and arrived in military uniform.
The imperial court is not a battlefield.
And His Lordship had only returned from a small victory.
So arriving late in his military uniform
— wasn't it swaggering around to show off his power?
Before His Majesty could say anything,
Zhang Lin, the censor, reprimanded him,
and rebuked him for major disrespect to His Majesty.
Prince Dun is always reckless.
He has always despised civil officials and scholars.
A censor's role is to give advice to the emperor
and point out the wrong-doings of the officials.
Only they would bluntly reprimand State Prince Dun in court.
You're correct, Lady Vertu.
State Prince Dun gave no response in court.
But on the way back,
he stopped Zhang Lin, and punched him until he passed out.
What?
Yes, ancient law says no one can assault a censor.
Moreover, State Prince Dun was at fault first.
This time, State Prince Dun has made everyone angry.
Now all the civil officials are urging
His Majesty to punish him severely
per the laws of the imperial court.
But State Prince Dun refuses to admit any wrongdoings.
He hasn't attended court for the last
two days, claiming he is sick.
This is absurd.
Everyone knows how His Majesty dealt with Lord VIII and Lord IX
when His Majesty ascended the throne.
With State Prince Dun exceeding his bounds,
It won't be hard for His Majesty to deal with him.
If His Majesty is truly angered,
then this will become complicated.
State Prince Dun has just made a contribution on the battlefield.
If His Majesty punishes him now,
I'm afraid it will have a negative impact on His Majesty's reputation.
But if this doesn't get dealt with properly,
it will damage the imperial court.
You're right, Lady Vertu.
It's because of this
that His Majesty has been staying
in the Hall of Mental Cultivation all day.
It's getting late. You should go check.
Let me think first.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
You have heard about what has happened
in the palace these last few days?
Yes, the news has caused an uproar.
Even though I reside in the harem, I've still heard of it.
Despite the many duties of court,
Your Majesty must take care your health as well.
I stewed Dong'e e-jiao with codonopsis.
Your Majesty, please have some.
It will supplement qi and help you calm down.
Since you've already heard about
Prince Dun's assault on a civil official.
How do you think I should handle this?
Should I follow the laws and punish State Prince Dun?
As head of state,
Your Majesty should of course follow the laws.
But it's not required to punish State Prince Dun.
I thought you would suggest punishing him.
Tell me what you think.
Your Majesty won't fault me for commenting on state affairs?
Don't worry, this is just an informal conversation.
I won't fault you for anything.
In my opinion,
in order to resolve the conflicts
between State Prince Dun and the officials,
the most important thing is to pacify both sides.
"When two tigers fight, one of them will be harmed."
No matter which side is harmed,
it will ultimately harm the foundation of our nation.
State Prince Dun has drawn considerable attention
returning from his victory.
If Your Majesty punishes His Lordship now,
it will cause discontent among the military officers.
However, it is not necessary for Your Majesty to
settle it by punishing State Prince Dun.
The civil officials are furious about the assault
but all they are expecting is just a response from Your Majesty.
And Your Majesty will give them one.
It would be best if State Prince Dun would
visit Zhang Lin and apologize to him.
Get State Prince Dun to go apologize?
He has a strong sense of superiority.
It might be easier to just kill him.
Not necessarily.
His Lordship fought the nation's enemies on the battlefields
and can be deemed a warrior.
Of all trials, what is most difficult for a warrior?
"Beautiful women are the most difficult trial for a warrior."
Only you would think of that, smarty-pants.
Your Majesty definitely knows "beautiful women
are the most difficult trial for a warrior."
I know nothing about state governance.
I know only trivial family things
-- "chicken feathers and garlic peels."
State Prince Dun holds his wife in high esteem.
If we put Her Ladyship to the task,
I believe she can bring His Lordship around.
I've encountered Her Ladyship a few times
and I know she's not a small-minded woman.
So who do you think
should be sent to persuade his wife?
If Your Majesty doesn't regard me as incompetent,
I will accept this duty.
In the entire harem,
only you can soothe my worries.
All these stipend-provided officials,
after half a day of clamor,
could only come up with ideas
to either punish him or not.
They are more useful than nothing.
I'm just a woman in Your Majesty's harem.
This is not my own idea,
but instead, an idea Your Majesty had which I guessed correctly.
The officials are familiar with books and ethics
but I understand Your Majesty.
I am able to make some conjectures about
the intent of Heaven within Your Majesty.
Huan Huan,
only you understand my heart.
But if State Prince Dun is set in his ways,
at some point, it might not serve to keep him.
If State Prince Dun keeps being imperious
and Your Majesty makes that decision,
it will be a great fortune for the people.
But now
it would not be beneficial to remove him.
You're right.
I resolve to appoint your father to an
important position at the Censorate
after this incident has been settled.
So he can denounce officials at any level.
Not only your father,
I will keep an eye out to also promote any talented official
who refuses to align themselves with
State Prince Dun and Nian Gengyao.
To avoid "beating the grass and startling the snakes,"
I'm still undecided about a few things.
In terms of appeasing State Prince Dun,
he and his wife already hold the greatest wealth and the highest distinction, what further awards could I grant?
"Pity the hearts and devotions of all parents under Heaven."
It seems that
we can only put some thought into their children.
He and his wife have a son and a daughter.
Their daughter holds the title of
Venerable Princess of Qingcheng [the third rank]
and I intend to make an exception and grant her
the title of Noble Princess [the second rank],
the same rank as the daughters of an emperor's concubines.
And I will grant his son the title of
Banner Prince [the fourth rank]
so he can inherit his father's honors.
Your Majesty is wise and thoughtful.
But in my humble opinion, Venerable Princess of
Qingcheng should not only be promoted
but also granted a new honorary name.
We can propose the title "Noble Princess
Gongding" [reverent and stable]
to remind her father of reverence and stability.
Of course,
Your Majesty wishes to resolve the quarrel with your brother
but we need to see whether or not
His Lordship appreciates Heaven's grace.
The princess should also be brought to the palace
and placed under the care of the Empress Dowager.
If something unforeseen happens in the future,
it will restrain State Prince Dun temporarily.
Absolutely, we will do what you suggest.
I will start drafting the decree immediately.
What were you saying earlier ...
Beautiful women are the most difficult trial for a warrior?
Your Majesty is teasing me.
I'm not a beautiful woman at all.
- Your Majesty.
- What is it?
You selected Lady An for tonight.
Lady An has sent over a few servants to confirm.
Tell her that she won't need to come here tonight.
Tell her to go to sleep early.
Lingrong has only just recently gained favor from Your Majesty.
Your Majesty should be more caring for her.
Don't make her wait in vain.
Allow me to take my leave.
Don't go yet.
I wonder how eagerly Lingrong
has been anticipating Your Majesty.
Your Majesty's words "carry the weight of nine dings"
[bronze ritual vessels]
You can't "eat your words" when it comes to women.
But I want to have you here.
As long as Your Majesty has me in your heart.
Why would I
contend with Lingrong for a day or night?
Take care on your way back.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
My Lady, Lady An just passed by.
It doesn't matter who His Majesty stays with
but instead,
who his heart stays with.
Jinxi
You, Jade and Vermillion must prepare for the visit of
State Prince Dun's wife to the palace in two days.
Understood.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
Peace to Your Highness.
Have a seat. Autumn, bring some tea.
Yes.
Spring, serve the tea.
I congratulate Your Highness on your full recovery.
When Your Ladyship visited a few months ago
to pay your respects to His Majesty,
I wanted to talk with you.
Sadly I was too busy and missed the chance.
What a shame.
Your Highness was with child.
I dared not disturb Your Highness.
Perhaps according to traditional ethics,
but according to family ethics
you are my sister.
We are all family, so we can treat each other intimately.
I am honored by Your Highness's kind words.
Your Majesty has been looking very well lately.
That's very kind of you.
After giving birth to Banner Prince Hongxuan,
you somehow look even more vibrant.
Banner Prince?
Is Your Majesty teasing me?
Hongxuan is only six years old
How could he be a Banner Prince?
Such is His Majesty's grace.
His Majesty loves Hongxuan the most out of his nephews.
Hongxuan may be young, but he is intelligent and adorable.
It was His Majesty's idea to bestow
the title of Banner Prince upon him early.
With careful guidance,
one day he may be like his father,
bringing peace and prosperity to the Great Qing.
I thank His Majesty in Hongxuan's stead.
That's not all.
His Majesty has good news coming in a pair.
He will grant Venerable Princess of Qingcheng
the title of Noble Princess
with the honorary name Noble Princess Gongding.
The Empress Dowager will be taking care of her from now on.
I thank His Majesty's heavenly grace.
However, the princess is only twelve years old.
I'm afraid she would cause trouble for the Empress Dowager.
Perhaps His Majesty might reconsider his decree.
His Majesty has few children.
This is a good thing for the Venerable Princess.
Over the course of the Qing Dynasty,
other princesses have been given the title Noble Princess as well,
but only right before marriage to honor their husbands.
His Majesty has established a new precedent
by granting the title of Noble Princess
to someone of such a young age.
All right. I am a little weary.
Please take your leave.
His Majesty's decree will be
delivered to your residence tonight.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
It's getting late. I will be taking my leave.
Your Highness.
It is not that late yet.
I would like to visit Your Highness's palace.
Would that be too much trouble?
Your Ladyship need not stand on ceremony.
I welcome guests who invite themselves.
We are family, not strangers.
Please come.
Please.
This tea is called "snow-drop jade".
It just arrived on the fastest courier.
Please try some and see
if it's deserving of Your Ladyship's liking.
Your Highness holds His Majesty's highest favor in the palace.
Naturally, Your Highness has the best of everything.
When I had my miscarriage,
Your Ladyship were the only one to visit me, despite my status.
I will always remember that.
I hope a day comes when I can repay Your Ladyship
for your heart-warming kindness.
Will Your Highness put in a word to His Majesty for me?
If I were you,
I would accept His Majesty's decree.
Let Empress Dowager take care of the princess.
Why does Your Highness say so?
As both a wife and a mother,
of course Your Ladyship must always
think of your husband and children,
and place their interests above your own.
Wouldn't Your Ladyship agree?
Prince Dun attacked a court official a few days ago,
and caused an uproar among the other officials.
Hopefully Prince Dun will consider
visiting Zhang Lin and apologizing to him.
With a temper like his,
he would never apologize to someone else.
If Your Ladyship cares for Prince Dun,
you must try and persuade him.
His Majesty wants to shield Prince Dun,
but ultimately it is Prince Dun who was at fault.
Zhang Lin is still unable to get out of bed.
His Majesty is upset, after all.
Prince Dun has a straightforward nature
and may stir up tensions again in the future.
If the princess is in the palace, she will be able to
speak to His Majesty in times of strife.
Wouldn't that be a good thing?
I will also suggest to His Majesty
that you be allowed to come to the palace
frequently to visit the princess.
What does Your Ladyship think?
Since His Majesty has put so much thought into this,
His Lordship and I cannot refuse his grace.
I thank Your Highness.
Please, have some tea.
I've finally learned
what it means to "anxiously await
something until one's eyes hurt".
Your Highness, please don't say that.
I wonder when
I will be able to see His Majesty again.
Your Highness need not worry.
Great General Nian has sent a messenger.
He is aware that Your Highness has been treated coldly recently,
and has made plans with State Prince Dun
to probe His Majesty's affections toward Your Highness.
I have already told you
not to bring this up with my brother.
Even if we were not to raise it with him
everyone in the palace knows how His Majesty
is treating Your Highness right now.
How could the Great General be unaware?
Out of all the things he could have done,
why did he choose to once again side with State Prince Dun?
He may owe Prince Dun some favors,
but they shouldn't be in overly close contact.
Now that Prince Dun's daughter has been
promoted to the second rank
and his son the fourth rank.
His Lordship is in high favor
and it's only natural that the Great General
would see him more frequently.
State Prince Dun is known for his
short temper and domineering attitude.
The Great General has ordered me to
ease Your Highness's worries.
General Nian said he only needs to do one thing for His Lordship
and then His Lordship will help Your Highness
regain His Majesty's favor.
Really?
With the Great General and His Lordship on your side,
there's nothing for Your Highness to worry about.
I do hope so.
- Song Zhi.
- Yes.
Light my Pleasancy for me.
It puts my mind at ease.
Yes.
His Majesty the Emperor.
- Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
- Rise.
Yesterday, State Prince Dun apologized to Zhang Lin in person.
Although it wasn't much of an apology
at least things have quieted down somewhat.
Huan Huan, you were of great help.
It is my duty to allay Your Majesty's worries.
I don't understand politics and can't help you in court affairs.
I can only chime in on small family matters.
This "snow-drop jade" is certainly excellent tea.
I know you like it so I sent the best to your palace.
Is it to your liking?
Of course.
I offered it to State Prince Dun's wife when she visited
but it didn't seem novel to Her Ladyship.
It was fortunate that Her Ladyship
didn't mind the tea and my hospitality.
Whatever tribute offerings the palace receives
Great General Nian has the same, if not better.
Now, even State Prince Dun has the same.
I never granted him that tea.
Where could he have gotten it?
Your Majesty need not be angry.
His assault of a civil official has raised "surging waves of chaos".
If any more gossip spreads after the waves calm,
it will tarnish his military achievements.
Does Your Majesty agree?
Your Majesty, I have brought you some water.
Your Majesty,
I've made a new sachet to present to Your Majesty.
Does Your Majesty like it?
Huan Huan made me a sachet a few days ago.
And I have it with me right now.
Having another would be unnecessary.
My needlework cannot compare to Sourire's.
Don't be foolish!
Lingrong's skills are far superior to my own.
His Majesty's belt and fan tassel
are both made by your hand.
That truly attests to your skill.
That's just because His Majesty
doesn't mind my coarse handwork.
This one is also good. I like it.
Ask Madam Orchid to put it in my sleep chamber.
My work is clumsy and inept,
I am glad as long as Your Majesty
appreciates the thought that went into it
The sachet Sourire made
suits Your Majesty's noble temperament.
The one I presented, however, looks unsophisticated.
I hope Your Majesty will pardon me.
There's nothing unsophisticated about it.
I understand the thought you put into it.
There's no need to ask for my pardon.
Sourire, your sewing and embroidery is getting even better.
If you make a sachet with a pair of mandarin ducks,
it will show your tender affection towards His Majesty.
His Majesty might like it even more.
That would be very thoughtful.
But if His Majesty goes about wearing the sachet day and night,
it will look overly sentimental.
Wearing a dragon sachet instead shows
His Majesty's heavenly authority.
But speaking of mandarin duck sachets,
I can make one for you if you like, Si Lang,
to put under your pillow.
What are you writing out?
The lyrical poem by Liu Yong
using the metre of "Rain Sounded Bell".
I like your calligraphy, but Liu Yong's poems are sorrowful.
“Hands held, gazing into each other's teary eyes,
Our sobbing breath chokes the words to be said.”
That poem does not match the present moment.
“This night brings a full moon and blooming flowers.
May My beloved and I long abide in this peaceful life.”
Here, take this and put it above your bed.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty is so affectionate towards Sourire.
This is a romantic story for the ages.
No one could ever enjoy such fortune as you, Sourire.
Your Majesty needs to make peace with Lingrong.
She's being silly and "sour as vinegar".
You always tease me, Sourire.
How would I dare to be sour about you and His Majesty?
Lingong is the mildest of all of you.
If she's as sour as vinegar,
it's vinegar that has only been fermenting for a month
which is barely sour at all.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.